A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
- Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, 2006-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 23308 emails.
  - Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries H. Barbara Reese Email, 2009-2010., Extent: 5694 emails
    This subseries contains 5694 emails in two PST files: BREESE.pst and GOVPOLibV2.pst. Barbara Reese served as Deputy Policy Director from January 2009 to January 2010. Reese lead the implementation of Virginia's $5 billion share of the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act including program and project design, implementation, reporting, and auditing. She also directed Virginia's $2 billion High Speed Rail Program and federal application process. Reese served as Legislative Director following the departure of Suzette Denslow in January 2009. She also served as Deputy Secretary of Transportation from July 2007 to January 2009.
    - BREESE.pst, 2009-2010.
      The BREESE.pst file contains 1485 emails sent and received by Barbara Reese between January 2009 and January 2010. There are 5 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications.
      Subjects include: American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus - projects, guidelines, web site development, implementation); fiscal 2010-2012 budget development; draft/outline of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2009, December 2009); Enterprise Zones; High Speed Rail; Recovery Zone Economic Development Bonds; REAL ID; Dulles Toll Road; Virginia Port Authority; Energy Performance PPEA; unemployment insurance/Virginia Employment Commission (VEC); and legislation.
      Notable email includes: email from Reese to Brian Shepard transmitting draft of 2009 Reconvened Session Vetoes and Amendments Talking Points, dated 6 April 2009.
      Correspondents include: Gena Boyle, Craig Burns, Pierce Homer, Tim Kaine, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Bill Shelton, Richard Sliwoski, D.B. Smit, Marilyn Tavenner, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, Stephen Walz, Eva Whitley, and Patricia Wright.
    - GOVPOLLibV2.pst, 2009-2010.
      The GOVPOLLibV2.pst file contains 4209 emails sent and received by Barbara Reese between January 2009 and January 2010. There are 29 privacy protected and confidential email in this PST file that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 2.2-3800. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing attorney-client communications and personal/personnel information.
      Subjects include: American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus - projects, guidelines, web site development, implementation); legislation (bill review, amendments, notes from conversations with members of the General Assembly about legislation, talking points, bill signing requests, administration position on select bills, and 2010 legislative proposals); Recovery Zone Economic Development Bonds; Qualified School Construction Bonds (QSCB); 2008-2010 budget cuts/amendments; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; 2010-2012 budget development; energy; unemployment insurance; 95/395 HOT lanes; Dulles Toll Road; TIGER Discretionary Grant program; Virginia Port Authority/APM Terminals; REAL ID; and rest area closures.
      Notable email includes: email exchange between Tim Kaine and Wayne Turnage on the administration's proposed process to manage stimulus money, 5 February 2009 (forwarded to Barbara Reese by Turnage); and email to senior administration officials from Wayne Turnage outlining work groups and procedures for economic stimulus package, 5, 2-3 February 2009.
      Correspondents include: Jeffrey Allen, Amber Amato, Kristen Amundson, Arthur Anderson, II, Janet Aylor, Charles Badger, Chris Bast, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Craig Burns, Young Ho Chang, Marc Cheatham, Ed Crooks, Don Darr, Kent Dickey, Nick Donohue, Manju Ganeriwala, Melinda Glazer, Lynette Hammond, Stephen Harms, Sherrie Harrington, Marilyn Harris, Mark Haskins, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Karen Jackson, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Malcolm Kerley, Wes Kleene, John Lawson, Alfonso Lopez, Michael Maul, Jo Anne Maxwell, Declan McManus, Kevin Page, Kate Paris, David Paylor, Megan Root, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Bill Shelton, Brian Shepard, D.B. Smit, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, Stephen Walz, Evie Whitley, and Patricia Wright.
- Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 22062 emails.
  The Communications Office Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the Communication Office of the Kaine Administration. This series contains 22064 emails in twelve (12) subseries. Subseries have been designated for A. Lynda Tran Email; B. Jeff Kraus Email; C. Gordon Hickey Email; D. Maurice A. Henderson II Email; E. Jeff Tiller Email; F. Robin Winchell Email; G. Michael Kelly Email; H. Lauren Cunningham Email; I. Doug Scott Email; J. Laura DeLibero Email; K. Amanda Howe Email; and L. Michaele White Email. There are 127 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records, and records containing personal/personnel information. The PST files for Delacey Skinner, Communications Director from January 2006 to December 2008, and Kevin Hall, Press Secretary from January 2006 to November 2007, were empty. However, email messages sent by Skinner and Hall may be found in the email files of other members of the Kaine Administration (Executive Office, Policy Office, Communications Office, etc.).
  The Communications Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. The Communications Office promotes the Governor's initiatives and priorities outside of government, as well as monitoring coverage of the Governor from outside, independent news sources. During Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2002-2010), the Communications Director strategically explained the Administration's priorities to the public in a variety of media. Any statement written or otherwise attributed to the Governor had to be cleared with Communications. The Communications Director was assisted in her responsibilities by a Press Secretary, additional press staff, a web master, and a photographer. In addition, the Communications Director oversaw the work of the Constituent Services Director whose staff members promptly responded to inquiries of the pubic received via mail, phone and email. The Communications Director was also a member of the Governor's Leadership Team. Delacey Skinner (January 2006-December 2008) and Lynda Tran (January 2009-January 2010) held this position during the Kaine administration (2006-2010).
  The Communications Director was assisted in her responsibilities by a Press Secretary (Kevin Hall, January 2006-October 2007, and Gordon Hickey, October 2007-January 2010). Jeff Kraus served as Senior Advisor to the Governor and Speech writer from January 2006 to January 2007.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries A. Lynda Tran Email, 2009-2010.
    The subseries contains 6844 email messages in one PST file: KaineLibLTran.pst. Lynda Tran served as Communications Director from January 2009 to January 2010. There are 86 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records and records containing personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: Chesapeake Bay; gubernatorial transition (Kaine to McDonnell); drafts/edits of press releases; review of Kaine quotes; responses to Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests for Governor Kaine's complete daily schedule (2009); responses to press inquiries; arrangements for President Barack Obama to call in to Governor Kaine's final Ask the Governor program on WTOP radio on 22 December 2009; drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2009 and 2010); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2009, December 2009); clemency (Jens Soering, Larry Bill Elliott, John Allen Muhammad, Norfolk Four, Edward Bell-all restricted); preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus-including development of Virginia stimulus website); Kaine administration accomplishments document; drafts of op-ed articles by Kaine (payday lending, end-of-term, Chesapeake Bay); event briefings/talking points; unemployment insurance; resignation of Tareq Salahi (White House party crasher) from Virginia Tourism Corporation board (2009); tax amnesty program (2009); smoking ban in restaurants; Dept. of Health Professions Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach; H1N1 strain of influenza; Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative (includes Biscuit Run property in Albemarle County); Asian oysters in the Chesapeake Bay; controversy over Department of State Police 2009 Virginia Terrorism Threat Assessment: Universities Possible Terror Portals; Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) (management issues); broadband program; rest area closures; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech.
    Notable email includes: email correspondence between Tran and Anita Kumar of the Washington Post, dated 9 December 2009, on resignation of Tareq Salahi from Virginia Tourism Authority (contains Salahi resignation letter); and email to Governor Kaine from Lynda Tran, dated 29 January 2009, containing her proposed communications plan.
    Correspondents include: Amber Amato, Viola Baskerville, Chris Bast, Bennett Blodgett, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Craig Burns, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Aneesh Chopra, Jeff Corbin, Beau Cribbs, Bob Crouch, Lauren Cunningham, Don Darr, Nick Donohue, Shane Emmett, Eric Finkbeiner, Marc Follmer, Greg Garner, Cathy Ghidotti, Phil Giaramita, Patrick Gottschalk, Mark Halperin, Lynette Hammond, Stephen Harms, Alleyn Harned, Sherrie Harrington, Marilyn Harris, Todd Haymore, Roz Helderman, Bernard Henderson, Fred Hiatt, Gordon Hickey, Anne Holton, Pierce Homer, Amanda Howe, Karen Jackson, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Martin Kent, Aryana Khalid, Anita Kumar, Bob Lewis, Travis Loop, Alfonso Lopez, J. Tucker Martin, John Marshall, Marianne McGhee, Megan McGuire, Christie Miller, James Nolan, Kate Paris, Len Pomata, Dena Potter, Barbara Reese, Karen Remley, Larry Roberts, Megan Root, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, Marilyn Tavenner, Dan Timberlake, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, and Julian Walker.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries B. Jeff Kraus Email, 2006-2007.
    The subseries contains 2705 email messages in one PST file: Jkraus.pst. Jeff Kraus served as Senior Advisor to the Governor and Speech writer from January 2006 to January 2007. Kraus served as Deputy Communications Director during Tim Kaine's 2005 gubernatorial campaign and Lt. Governor Kaine's Communications Director (2003-2005). He left the administration in January 2007 for a position with the Virginia Community College System. Kraus wrote speeches, op-ed pieces, talking points, and letters to government officials for Governor Kaine. Kraus also wrote several speeches for First Lady Ann Holton. He served as Kaine's liaison for special projects including Jamestown 2007 commemoration.
    Subjects include: Freedman's Bank historical marker in Richmond; drafts of speeches, remarks, talking points, etc. for Governor Kaine (includes background information); drafts of speeches and remarks for First Lady Anne Holton (including background information); draft of piece by Kaine describing his 12-17 March 2006 trip to visit Virginia troops in Iraq, Kuwait and Afghanistan; Jamestown 2007 planning (including issues related to Tareq Salahi); 2006 transportation plan (speeches, talking points and Town Hall meetings); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2006 and December 2006); and drafts of Kaine's biography for web site.
    Correspondents include: Viola Baskerville, Preston Bryant, Kim Busch, James Carr, Marc Cheatham, Aneesh Chopra, Kevin Crossett, B. Hayes Framme, Manju Ganeriwala, Cathy Ghidotti, Steven Gould, Kevin Hall, Sherrie Harrington, Carrie Henderson, Maurcie Henderson, II, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Pierce Homer, Tim Kaine, Bill Leighty, Emily Lockhart, John Marshall, Jane Minerly, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Missy Neff, Maribel Ramos, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Tareq Salahi, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Shepard, Rick Siger, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage and Richard Zorn.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries C. Gordon Hickey Email, 2007-2010.
    The subseries contains 6250 email messages in one PST file: KaineLibGHickey.pst. Hickey served as Press Secretary to Governor Kaine from October 2007 to January 2010. Hickey had previously worked as a reporter for the Richmond Times Dispatch. As Press Secretary, Hickey answered all media inquiries concerning the Kaine's administration on issues. He provided background information to reporters, approved quotes from the Governor, and wrote, edited, and approved press releases. Hickey, as member of the Governor's Leadership Team, advised the Governor on media issues. There are 30 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records and records containing personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: transportation (abusive driver fees, rest stops, legislation); background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points (includes press releases never issued); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus-criteria for projects and creation of web site); legislation; budget issues/press inquiries; media queries on clemency, restoration of rights, and blanket restoration of rights; Dominion Power's Wise County project; Dulles Toll Road; H1N1 strain of influenza; media requests for comments for news stories; requests by administration for corrections in news stories; preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration, costs for Virginia and localities and reimbursement by the federal government for those expenses; Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative; and approval of Kaine quotes for press releases.
    Notable email includes: email thread on the Wise County power plant/mountaintop mining, dated 21 February 2008, started by Governor Kaine on 18 February 2008; email from Gordon Hickey, dated 22 April 2009, to Wayne Turnage, containing a spread sheet attachment listing all "projects lost" by the Virginia Economic Development Partnership from January 2005 to 15 April 2009. The spread sheet lists: name of project/company, lost date, approved amount, state won, primary reason lost, and real reason lost; email from Gordon Hickey, dated 13 May 2009, to Wayne Turnage, containing a spread sheet attachment listing Virginia Announcements of Employment Creation and Capital Investment from 1 January 1998 to 22 April 2009; Governor's Office procedures for the execution of Edward Nathan Bell, 19 February 2009 (restricted); and email from Gordon Hickey, dated 23 April 2009, to Jeff Tiller forwarding an email exchange between Tim Kaine and Tim Dunn, re: Amendment 596.
    Correspondents include: Viola Baskerville, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Craig Burns, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Jeff Corbin, Lauren Cunningham, Nick Donohue, Gary Emerling, Manju Ganeriwala, Greg Garner, Kathy Glazer, Frank Green, Todd Haymore, Roz Helderman, Bernard Henderson, Pierce Homer, Drew Houff, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Anita Kumar, Bob Lewis, Alfonso Lopez, J. Tucker Martin, Seth McLaughlin, Olympia Meola, Christie Miller, Jim Nolan, Dena Potter, Charles Pyle, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Jeff Schapiro, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, J. Garren Shipley, Delacey Skinner, Bob Spieldenner, Tamra Talmadge-Anderson, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Lynda Tran, Larry Traylor, Wayne Turnage, Jody Wagner, Julian Walker, Stephen Walz, Suzanne West, Tyler Whitley, and Michael Paul Williams.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries D. Maurice A. Henderson, II Email, 2006-2007.
    The subseries contains 572 email messages in one PST file: Inbox.pst. Henderson served as Deputy Press Secretary to Governor Kaine from March 2006 to June 2007.
    Subjects include: First Lady press releases; photographs of First Lady at public events; First Lady event briefings; talking points and background information for Governor's events; and photographs of Governor Kaine (as attachments) taken by Michaele White, Governor's Photographer.
    Notable email includes: email from Bill Leighty, dated 23 August 2006, to Jeff Kraus, listing the Kaine Administration's accomplishments (in email to Henderson sent 16 November 2006).
    Correspondents include: Kevin Hall, Asha Holloman, Bill Leighty, Delacey Skinner, Michaele White, and Robin Winchell.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries E. Jeff Tiller Email, 2006-2008.
    The subseries contains 425 email messages in one PST file: 2007Libjtiller.pst. Jeff Tiller served as Press Aide (January-December 2006), Assistant Press Secretary from (January 2007 to July 2007), and Deputy Press Secretary (August 2007 to July 2008).
    Subjects include: background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points; approval of Kaine quotes for press releases; logistics for Cabinet Community Days; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (creation of panel and release of Virginia Tech Review Panel report).
    Correspondents include: Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Kevin Hall, Gordon Hickey, Tim Kaine, Jim Kudla, and Delacey Skinner.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries F. Robin Winchell Email, 2005-2006.
    The subseries contains 1313 email messages in one PST file: inbox.pst. Robin Winchell served as Senior Press Aide in the Kaine Administration from January 2006 to May 2006. She previously worked as a Communications Assistant to the 2005 Kaine for Governor campaign. Winchell left the administration in May 2006 to take a position as Communications Director for Congressman Charlie Melancon (LA-03). Winchell wrote and distributed press releases, talking points, and op-eds. She also directed communications for First Lady Anne Holton.
    Subjects include: communications for First Lady Anne Holton including writing press releases, news releases, event briefing forms, and coordinating public appearances and interviews; news clips compiled for Tim Kaine's gubernatorial campaign (2005); photographs (as attachments from Michaele White) of Governor Kaine events; Winchell's weekly reports from January to May 2006; and drafts of press releases and talking points.
    Correspondents include: Sindy Benavides, Katie Boyer, Kimberly Busch, Kevin Hall, Maurice A. Henderson, II, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Tim Kaine, Jeff Kraus, Bill Leighty, Rick Siger, Delacey Skinner, Martha Steger, Jeff Tiller, and Michaele White.
  - Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries G. Michael Kelly Email, 2007-2010., Extent: 3074 emails
    This subseries contains 3074 emails in two PST files: MKELLY.PST and KaineLibMKelly.pst. Michael Kelly served as a Press Aide (September 2007 to May 2009) and Assistant Press Secretary (May 2009-January 2010) in the Kaine administration from September 2007 to January 2010. Kelly compiled daily news clippings, assisted with press events, drafted press releases, coordinated with agencies and organizations on media-related requests, lead advance work for key events statewide including Cabinet Community Days, and acted as on-the-record spokesperson for Governor Kaine as appropriate.
    - MKELLY.PST, 2007-2010.
      The MKELLY.PST file contains 1188 emails sent and received by Michael Kelly between September 2007 and January 2010. There are 9 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.
      Subjects include: background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points (includes press releases never issued); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009; legislation; budget issues/press inquiries; media queries on clemency; compiling news clippings, Cabinet Day events; briefing material for Governor's events; drafting Kaine quotes for press releases; notes from news conferences held by Governor Kaine, General Assembly Republicans, etc.; and notes from press "gaggles" held by Governor Kaine.
      Correspondents include: Chris Bast, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Lauren Cunningham, Nick Donohue, Cathy Ghidotti, Alleyn Harned, Carrie Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Amanda Howe, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Lynda Tran, and Wayne Turnage.
    - KaineLibMKelly.pst, 2007-2010.
      The KaineLibMKelly.pst file contains 1886 emails sent and received by Michael Kelly between September 2007 and January 2010. There are 2 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: public safety.
      Subjects include: background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points; event briefing forms prepared for Scheduling Office (includes event, date/time, attire, location, contact information, staff assigned to Governor, Governor's role in event, talking points, and additional information; many appear to be drafts); Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach; cabinet day(s); notes from news conferences held by Governor Kaine, General Assembly Republicans, etc.; scripts for Governor Kaine's Public Service Announcements (PSA); and media/external inquiries and requests.
      Notable email includes: email thread between Marilyn Tavenner, Secretary of Health and Human Resources, and Sandra Ryals, Director, Department of Health Professionals, dated 7 August 2009, responding to New York Times inquiry about Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach.